<articles>
    <article id="a1">
        <title>Introduction to XQuery</title>
        <author>Jane Smith</author>
        <year>2023</year>
        <category>tutorial</category>
        <body>XQuery is a powerful functional language designed for querying and transforming XML data. It is the standard query language for XML databases and is widely used in digital humanities, publishing, and data integration. XQuery supports FLWOR expressions, XPath navigation, and user-defined functions.</body>
    </article>
    <article id="a2">
        <title>Full-Text Search in eXist-db</title>
        <author>John Doe</author>
        <year>2024</year>
        <category>reference</category>
        <body>eXist-db provides powerful full-text search capabilities built on Apache Lucene. The ft:query function enables keyword search, phrase matching, wildcard queries, and fuzzy matching. Combined with KWIC snippets, developers can build sophisticated search interfaces with minimal effort.</body>
    </article>
    <article id="a3">
        <title>Vector Embeddings for Semantic Search</title>
        <author>Alice Chen</author>
        <year>2025</year>
        <category>research</category>
        <body>Vector embeddings represent text as dense numerical arrays that capture semantic meaning. Similar concepts have similar vectors, enabling semantic search that goes beyond keyword matching. Modern embedding models like all-MiniLM-L6-v2 produce 384-dimensional vectors suitable for similarity search.</body>
    </article>
    <article id="a4">
        <title>Building REST APIs with RESTXQ</title>
        <author>Jane Smith</author>
        <year>2024</year>
        <category>tutorial</category>
        <body>RESTXQ is a standard for mapping HTTP requests to XQuery functions using annotations. In eXist-db, RESTXQ provides a clean way to build web APIs. Functions are annotated with HTTP methods, paths, and content types, making it easy to create RESTful services backed by XML data.</body>
    </article>
    <article id="a5">
        <title>Digital Humanities and XML</title>
        <author>Maria Garcia</author>
        <year>2023</year>
        <category>research</category>
        <body>XML and TEI encoding have become central to digital humanities projects. Scholars use XML databases like eXist-db to store, search, and analyze historical texts. Full-text search with faceted navigation allows researchers to explore large corpora interactively, discovering patterns across thousands of documents.</body>
    </article>
    <article id="a6">
        <title>Machine Learning Meets XML Databases</title>
        <author>Alice Chen</author>
        <year>2025</year>
        <category>research</category>
        <body>The integration of machine learning with XML databases opens new possibilities for intelligent document processing. Vector search enables semantic similarity queries alongside traditional full-text search. Hybrid approaches combine keyword precision with semantic understanding for more relevant results.</body>
    </article>
</articles>
