<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Edition Landing Page</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="hero" xml:lang="en">
            <head>Jinks<hi rend="strong">edition</hi></head>
            <p>This site presents the results of the digital humanities projects created with TEI
               Publisher and Jinks. It is a part of the environment for the development of digital
               scholarly editions and a space for their presentation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="about" xml:lang="en" n="About">
            <head>Working environment for creating and publishing of digital scholarly
               editions</head>
            <p>Jinks application manager is designed as a working environment for creating and
               publishing of digital scholarly editions. Editions created with this framework are
               aiming to meet the varied needs of several humanities disciplines (textual
               scholarship, literary studies, linguistics, history and more). Jinks builds on what
               is common, at the same time providing the choice and customisation possibilities to
               the editors and developers.</p>
            <p>The platform follows the international standard for the encoding of textual data,
               TEI, and bases its visualisations on TEI Publisher. As a result, it enables
               publication of different types of material: from the basic presentation of texts and
               documents in digital form to the most complex scholarly editions. There is room for
               various forms of textual delivery (transcriptions, translations, facsimiles) and
               annotations.</p>
            <p>Tools and working environment are not enough. To best serve the needs of editors, a
               consistent and efficient process for creating and publishing digital scholarly
               editions is needed. This project is offering such a process. It includes sets of good
               practices and workflows and takes into account both how scholarly editors work and
               how IT specialists, responsible for the technical side of editions, complete their
               tasks.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:lang="en" n="More">
            <head>Other resources</head>
            <p>Use this section to provide short descriptions and links to other resources in the
               collection.</p>
            <p>The Jinks edition project is brought to life by a dedicated team of historians,
               digital archivists, and designers passionate about Renaissance history</p>
            <div>
               <head>Collection of sources encoded with the TEI standard</head>
               <p>Fascinating collection of sources encoded in the TEI standard, comprising records
                  of rulers and individuals belonging to the social elite of European states provide
                  insight into the mechanisms of power, the relationship between the center and the
                  peripheries of a state, and the way of life of different social groups. They
                  reveal the mobility of their representatives, networks of contacts, and their
                  engagement in social, political, and economic life.</p>
               <p><ref target="#" rend="explore-link">Explore</ref></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Collection of sources encoded with the TEI standard</head>
               <p>Fascinating collection of sources encoded in the TEI standard, comprising records
                  of rulers and individuals belonging to the social elite of European states provide
                  insight into the mechanisms of power, the relationship between the center and the
                  peripheries of a state, and the way of life of different social groups. They
                  reveal the mobility of their representatives, networks of contacts, and their
                  engagement in social, political, and economic life.</p>
               <p><ref target="#" rend="explore-link">Explore</ref></p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="team" xml:lang="en" n="Core Team">
            <head>Team</head>
            <p>The Jinks edition project is brought to life by a dedicated team of historians,
               digital archivists, and designers passionate about Renaissance history</p>
            <listPerson>
               <person n="project managment">
                  <persName>Coco</persName>
                  <occupation>System architect</occupation>
                  <ptr type="avatar" target="resources/images/team/dog.jpg"/>
                  <note>Happily fetches new features while herding the pack towards technical excellence.</note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listOrg>
               <org n="e-editiones">
                  <orgName>e-editiones</orgName>
                  <roleName>Scholarly society</roleName>
                  <ptr type="logo" target="resources/images/e-editiones-logo-color.svg"/>
                  <ptr type="email" target="mailto:info@e-editiones.org"/>
                  <note><ref target="https://www.e-editiones.org/">e-editiones</ref> is an international non profit society bringing together edition projects, cultural heritage institutions, scholars, and developers to empower digital projects by promoting open standards and community collaboration – with the ultimate goal of helping to sustain editions far into the future.</note>
               </org>
               <org n="jinntec">
                  <orgName>Jinntec GmbH</orgName>
                  <roleName>Software solutions</roleName>
                  <ptr type="logo" target="resources/images/jinntec.svg"/>
                  <ptr type="email" target="mailto:info@jinntec.de"/>
                  <note>Software solutions with a touch of magic: we believe in the importance of cultural heritage - our tools help to preserve and disseminate it with sustainable technologies based on Open Source software and Open Standard. From assisted production workflows and data curation to publishing online or in print - [we have you covered](https://www.jinntec.de/).</note>
               </org>
            </listOrg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
