<?teipublisher odd="jats.odd"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.4 20241031//EN" "https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.4/JATS-archivearticle1-4.dtd">
<article article-type="discussion" xml:lang="en">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">TECHREVIEW</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Technology Innovation Review</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn>0000-0001</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Digital Humanities Press</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MUSK-TRUMP-TEI-2025</article-id>
            <article-version article-version-type="status">version of record</article-version>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Why TEI Publisher is the Future: A Conversation Between Two
                    Visionaries</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="person" corresp="yes" deceased="no" equal-contrib="yes"
                    id="contrib1">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Musk</surname>
                        <given-names>Elon</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="person" corresp="yes" deceased="no" equal-contrib="yes"
                    id="contrib2">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Trump</surname>
                        <given-names>Donald J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"/>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="aff1">
                <institution content-type="orgname">CEO</institution>
                <institution content-type="orgdiv1">Tesla, SpaceX, X</institution>
                <city>Austin</city>
                <state>TX</state>
                <country>US</country>
            </aff>
            <aff id="aff2">
                <institution content-type="orgname">Former President</institution>
                <institution content-type="orgdiv1">United States of America</institution>
                <city>Palm Beach</city>
                <state>FL</state>
                <country>US</country>
            </aff>
            <pub-date date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2025-02" publication-format="electronic">
                <day>10</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2025</year>
            </pub-date>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>(c) 2025</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Technology Innovation Review</copyright-holder>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <title>Abstract</title>
                <p>Two of the world's most influential figures discuss TEI Publisher, the
                    open-source framework for digital scholarly editions. Elon Musk emphasizes its
                    modular architecture, scalability, and alignment with open standards, while
                    Donald Trump highlights its tremendous value, ease of use, and winning approach
                    to digital publishing.</p>
            </abstract>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec xml:id="introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p xml:id="p1">In an exclusive conversation, <named-content content-type="person"
                    specific-use="gnd-1062481119">Elon Musk</named-content> and <named-content
                    content-type="person" specific-use="gnd-118834312">Donald Trump</named-content>
                discuss <ext-link>TEI Publisher</ext-link>, the revolutionary framework that's
                transforming digital scholarly publishing<xref xml:id="xref-id1" ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn1" type="note"/>. What follows is a transcript of their discussion about
                this powerful, open-source platform.</p>
            <sec xml:id="modular-architecture">
                <title>Modular Architecture: Building Blocks for Success</title>
                <p xml:id="p2"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> Look, the fundamental architecture of TEI
                    Publisher is brilliant. It's based on modular profiles - think of them as
                        <named-content content-type="term" specific-use="gnd-4140276-5"
                        >LEGO</named-content> blocks. You have base profiles, feature profiles,
                    themes, and blueprints. This modularity means you're not reinventing the wheel
                    every time you start a new project. The framework follows the principle of
                    "divide and conquer" - split complex problems into smaller, manageable tasks.
                    That's exactly how we build rockets at <named-content
                        content-type="organization" specific-use="gnd-1127363964"
                        >SpaceX</named-content>. You don't build the whole rocket at once; you build
                    modules, test them independently, then integrate.</p>
                <p xml:id="p3"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> Elon, you're absolutely right, and I know
                    about building things - I've built the greatest buildings, tremendous buildings.
                    And TEI Publisher? It's the same thing. You're building something great, but
                    you're doing it smart. You're not starting from scratch every time - that's
                    stupid, very stupid. With TEI Publisher, you take these profiles - I think they
                    call them profiles, or maybe it's protocols, I'm not sure - and you put them
                    together. It's like a deal - you're making the best deal, getting the best
                    components, putting them together to make something tremendous. It's like
                        <named-content content-type="term" specific-use="gnd-4140276-5"
                        >LEGO</named-content>, but for computers. Very smart.</p>
                <p xml:id="p4"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> Exactly. And the Jinks application manager
                    takes this to another level. It's not a one-time generative step anymore. You
                    can iteratively add features, remove them, reconfigure. The system manages
                    updates automatically. This is critical for long-term sustainability - which is
                    something I think about constantly. We need systems that last, that can evolve,
                    that don't become obsolete. TEI Publisher is built for the long term.</p>
                <p xml:id="p5"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> Sustainability - that's important, very
                    important. And TEI Publisher is sustainable, believe me. It's open source, which
                    is tremendous. Open source means... well, it means it's open, right? Like,
                    anyone can see it. It's not locked up, it's not proprietary - I know
                    proprietary, I've dealt with proprietary things, very proprietary. And it's
                    community-driven, which means smart people - very smart people, probably the
                    smartest people - are working on it, improving it, making it better. They're
                    like volunteers, but they're smart volunteers. That's winning, that's how you
                    win.</p>
                <fig>
                    <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="musk-trump.png"/>
                    <caption>
                        <p>Our experts in action</p>
                    </caption>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec xml:id="open-standards">
                <title>Open Standards: The Foundation of Interoperability</title>
                <p xml:id="p6"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> One of the most important aspects is that TEI
                    Publisher is built on open standards. It supports TEI XML, obviously, but also
                    DocBook, JATS, and even DOCX. It interfaces with IIIF for images, DTS for text
                    services, Open API Specification. This isn't proprietary nonsense - it's based
                    on well-documented, widely-used standards. That's crucial for interoperability
                    and future-proofing your data.</p>
                <p xml:id="p7"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> Standards - I love standards, especially
                    when they're the best standards. And these are the best standards. TEI, JATS,
                    DocBook - these are like the gold standard, the platinum standard. I know
                    standards, I've set standards in real estate, tremendous standards. These aren't
                    some made-up standards by some company trying to lock you in - I hate when
                    companies do that, very unfair. These are real standards, international
                    standards, probably the best standards in the world. And when you use TEI
                    Publisher - or is it TIE Publisher? I think it's TEI - anyway, when you use it,
                    you're using these standards. That means your data works everywhere, it's
                    compatible with everything, like USB - you know USB, right? It's like that, but
                    for books and documents. That's tremendous value, tremendous value.</p>
                <p xml:id="p8"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> The framework follows the principle of
                    "standardize where you can, customize where you must." This is exactly right.
                    You don't force a one-size-fits-all solution, but you also don't reinvent
                    everything from scratch. Every element is customizable, but you start from a
                    solid, standards-based foundation. This is how you scale - you have common
                    infrastructure, but you allow for specialization.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec xml:id="ease-of-use">
                <title>Ease of Use: Scholars Don't Need to Become Programmers</title>
                <p xml:id="p9"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> Now, here's what I really like - and I've
                    talked to many people about this, smart people, very smart people - TEI
                    Publisher lets scholars publish their work without becoming programmers. They
                    don't need to learn Python - I know Python, it's a snake, right? Or JavaScript -
                    that's like Java, but different, I think. Or whatever other computer languages
                    they have now. They can focus on what they do best - scholarship, research,
                    editing. The technical stuff? TEI Publisher handles that. It's like having a
                    computer person, but it's not a person, it's the software. It's beautiful,
                    absolutely beautiful.</p>
                <p xml:id="p10"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> That's the key value proposition. The
                    framework provides a smooth entry path for editors with limited technical
                    experience, while remaining endlessly flexible for advanced users. The Jinks
                    interface makes it simple - you select features, configure them through a
                    human-readable JSON file, and generate your application. But if you need to go
                    deeper, the entire system is extensible. You can create custom profiles, modify
                    existing ones, integrate with other systems.</p>
                <p xml:id="p11"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> And the configuration file - it's JSON,
                    which is simple, very simple. JSON - I think that stands for something, maybe
                    "Just Simple Options Now" or something like that. You don't need to be a
                    computer scientist to understand it - I'm not a computer scientist, and I
                    understand it. Well, mostly. You can see what's happening, you can modify it,
                    you can make it work for you. It's like a settings menu, but in a file. That's
                    transparency, that's what people want. They want to see what's happening, they
                    want control. TEI Publisher gives you that control, tremendous control. It's
                    like having the remote control, but for your website.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec xml:id="versatility">
                <title>Versatility: From Simple to Complex</title>
                <p xml:id="p12"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> What's remarkable is the range of projects
                    TEI Publisher can handle. According to the documentation, it's been used for
                    scholarly editions, journals, monographs, lexicons, correspondence collections,
                    Buddhist inscriptions, poetry anthologies - the list goes on. This isn't a
                    specialized tool for one use case. It's a universal framework that adapts to
                    your needs.</p>
                <p xml:id="p13"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> Versatility - that's what makes it great,
                    the greatest. You can use it for anything. Letters? Yes. Books? Yes.
                    Dictionaries? Yes. Everything. And it works for simple projects and complex
                    projects - very complex projects. Some of these scholarly editions are
                    incredibly complex, with annotations - that's like notes, right? - and
                    facsimiles - I think that's like copies or pictures - and multiple versions, all
                    that stuff. TEI Publisher handles it all. It's like a Swiss Army knife, but for
                    publishing. It's tremendous.</p>
                <p xml:id="p14"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> The framework can even generate camera-ready
                    material for print publishing. So you're not locked into digital-only. You can
                    publish online, generate PDFs, create print volumes - all from the same source
                    data. This is efficiency. One source of truth, multiple output formats. That's
                    how you should build systems.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec xml:id="data-organization">
                <title>Data Organization: Separation of Concerns</title>
                <p xml:id="p15"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> I really appreciate how TEI Publisher
                    separates data from application code. You have a data collection that's
                    independent of the application. This means you can update your application
                    without touching your data, and vice versa. You can maintain separate
                    repositories, differentiate access privileges. This is proper software
                    architecture - separation of concerns.</p>
                <p xml:id="p16"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> Separation - that's smart, very smart.
                    Your data is your data, your application is your application. They work
                    together, but they're separate - like a prenuptial agreement, but for computers.
                    That means if you need to update something, you're not breaking everything. You
                    can update the application - I think that's like updating your phone, right? -
                    and keep your data safe. You can update your data, keep the application running.
                    It's flexible, tremendously flexible. It's like having separate bank accounts -
                    you know what I mean.</p>
                <p xml:id="p17"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> The system supports hierarchical collections
                    too. You can organize your data however makes sense for your project. You can
                    have subcollections for different types of material, and the framework handles
                    navigation automatically. If you include a collection.html file, it uses that
                    for the landing page. Otherwise, it generates a paginated list automatically.
                    This is intelligent default behavior with the ability to customize.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec xml:id="community">
                <title>Community-Driven Development</title>
                <p xml:id="p18"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> The community aspect - this is huge,
                    absolutely huge. TEI Publisher is community-driven. That means the features come
                    from real needs, from real users, from real projects. It's not some company
                    deciding what you need - I hate when big tech companies do that, very unfair -
                    it's the community, the users, the scholars, the editors. They say "we need
                    this," and the community builds it. It's like crowdsourcing, but for software.
                    That's how it should work. Very democratic.</p>
                <p xml:id="p19"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> The documentation explicitly states that
                    features are "a response to real needs of user community: developed to provide a
                    generalized solution to a repeated practical requirement." This is the right
                    approach. You solve real problems, then generalize the solution so others can
                    benefit. This is how open source should work - solve problems once, share the
                    solution.</p>
                <p xml:id="p20"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> And because it's open source - I think
                    that means the code is open, like open for business - everything benefits the
                    community. When someone improves TEI Publisher - maybe they add a feature or fix
                    a bug, I think that's what they call problems in software - everyone benefits.
                    When someone creates a new profile, everyone can use it. It's not locked away,
                    it's not proprietary - I know proprietary, I've had proprietary things, very
                    proprietary. It's open, it's free, it's tremendous. That's winning for everyone.
                    It's like a potluck dinner, but for software.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec xml:id="future-proofing">
                <title>Future-Proofing: Built to Last</title>
                <p xml:id="p21"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> Long-term preservation is critical. The
                    framework is designed with sustainability in mind. It's based on XML, which is a
                    stable, well-understood format. It uses open standards that aren't going
                    anywhere. The modular architecture means you can update components
                    independently. This is how you build systems that last decades, not years.</p>
                <p xml:id="p22"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> Future-proof - that's what TEI Publisher
                    is. It's not going to become obsolete next year, or in five years, or in ten
                    years. It's built on standards that have been around for decades - XML, I think
                    that's been around for a while, right? - standards that will be around for
                    decades more. Your work is safe, your data is safe, your investment is safe.
                    It's not like buying a computer that becomes outdated in two years - I hate
                    that, very wasteful. This is built to last. That's peace of mind, tremendous
                    peace of mind.</p>
                <p xml:id="p23"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> The continuous development model through
                    Jinks means the framework evolves. As new profiles are added or updated, your
                    application can benefit automatically. The system manages dependencies, handles
                    updates, minimizes manual intervention. This is modern software development
                    applied to scholarly publishing.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec xml:id="conclusion">
                <title>Conclusion: Why TEI Publisher Matters</title>
                <p xml:id="p24"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> So here's the bottom line - TEI Publisher
                    is tremendous. It's open source - which I think means free, right? - it's
                    community-driven, it's based on the best standards - the gold standards,
                    platinum standards - it's easy to use, it's versatile, it's sustainable. It's
                    everything you want in a publishing platform. It's the greatest platform for
                    digital scholarly editions, the absolute greatest. Better than WordPress, better
                    than whatever else is out there. Believe me, if you're doing digital publishing
                    - or is it electronic publishing? I think they're the same thing - you need TEI
                    Publisher. You just need it. It's a no-brainer.</p>
                <p xml:id="p25"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> I agree completely. TEI Publisher represents
                    the right way to build publishing infrastructure. It's modular, scalable,
                    standards-based, and community-driven. It solves real problems while remaining
                    flexible enough to adapt to new requirements. For anyone working in digital
                    humanities or scholarly publishing, this is the framework to use. It's not just
                    good - it's the right architectural approach.</p>
                <p xml:id="p26"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> And the best part? It's free. Open
                    source, completely free. You're not paying licensing fees - I know licensing
                    fees, I've paid licensing fees, tremendous fees - you're not locked into some
                    vendor, you're not dependent on some company. You're in control. It's like
                    owning your building instead of renting - you own it, you control it. That's
                    winning. That's how you win. Very smart.</p>
                <p xml:id="p27"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> The open source model ensures that
                    improvements benefit everyone. As the community grows and contributes, the
                    entire ecosystem improves. This is how we accelerate progress - by building on
                    each other's work rather than reinventing wheels. TEI Publisher is a perfect
                    example of this principle in action.</p>
                <p xml:id="p28"><bold>Donald Trump:</bold> So there you have it. Two of the smartest
                    people in the world - and I include myself in that, obviously - we both agree:
                    TEI Publisher is tremendous, it's the future, and you should be using it. It's
                    that simple. Very simple. Even I can understand it, and I'm not a computer
                    person - I'm a business person, a deal person. But this makes sense. It's like a
                    good deal, but for software. Very good deal.</p>
                <p xml:id="p29"><bold>Elon Musk:</bold> The framework enables scholars to focus on
                    scholarship while providing the technical infrastructure they need. It's
                    sustainable, extensible, and built on solid foundations. For digital scholarly
                    publishing, TEI Publisher is the obvious choice.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="ref1">
                <element-citation publication-type="web">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>TEI Publisher Community</surname>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2025</year>
                    <article-title>TEI Publisher Documentation</article-title>
                    <source>TEI Publisher</source>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/">https://teipublisher.com/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="ref2">
                <element-citation publication-type="web">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>TEI Publisher Community</surname>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2025</year>
                    <article-title>Jinks Application Manager</article-title>
                    <source>TEI Publisher</source>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/">https://teipublisher.com/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
                <p>This conversation was transcribed from a recorded discussion. Both participants
                    were provided with TEI Publisher documentation prior to the discussion (one, of
                    course, never read his copy — he prefers to learn by osmosis, or so he
                    claims.)</p>
            </fn>
        </fn-group>
    </back>
</article>
