<?teipublisher odd="docbook.odd" template="documentation.html" depth="5" fill="2" media="latex print fo epub markdown"?>
<?xml-model href="https://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
    <info>
        <title>Quickstart</title>
        <author>
            <orgname>TEI Publisher Community</orgname>
        </author>
        <keywordset vocab="#genre">
            <keyword>Documentation</keyword>
        </keywordset>
        <abstract>
            <para>Start here. Introduces key concepts, installation instructions and a guided
                tour.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>
    <section xml:id="introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <section xml:id="introduction-foreword">
            <para>TEI Publisher provides a flexible and sustainable <emphasis>toolbox</emphasis>
                which enables scholars with limited technical skills to publish their material
                without forcing it into a one-size-fits-all framework. Our mantra is to stop
                reinventing the wheel with every new digital project and reuse what others have
                already built instead. And, most importantly, help to improve the shared base by
                adding what's missing into the communal pool. <note role="todo"> link to how to
                    contribute/extend </note>
            </para>
            <para>TEI Publisher provides a smooth and fast entry path for editors with little
                technical experience while remaining endlessly flexible and extensible for advanced
                users. </para>
            <para>Numerous projects realized with TEI Publisher worldwide prove that it is:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a truly universal tool for any kind of digital publication, from scholarly
                        editions to journals, monographs, lexicons, and much more</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>suitable even for very complex and multi-faceted material</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>sustainable and future-proof</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>capable of generating high quality, camera ready material for print
                        publishing</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>suitable for any XML, not only TEI (this documentation is written in
                        DocBook!)</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <section xml:id="intro-jinks">
                <title>Overview</title>
                <para> Starting with the version 10, based on Jinks application manager, the core
                    TEI Publisher idea of assembling an edition from the modular
                        <emphasis>"lego"</emphasis> blocks is taken to the next level. Despite the
                    changes to the interface and internal reorganization, advanced users will
                    nevertheless find most underlying concepts and components slightly changed but
                    still recognizable. </para>
                <para>Version 10 substantially extends the <emphasis>toolbox</emphasis> idea of
                    simple, recombinable blocks: the core of TEI Publisher itself is now decomposed
                    into a set of small, modular profiles, which can be combined and configured to
                    assemble concrete applications. Each profile provides end-to-end implementation
                    for a particular aspect of a digital edition, e.g. support for a certain input
                    format, integration of facsimile images, timelines or map display.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Assembling an application</title>
                <para>An actual application is created by selecting desired features and customizing
                    their configuration. This is achieved through a central configuration file,
                    which can be easily edited through the user interface. Human-readable structure
                    of the configuration file coupled with syntax suggestions in this step greatly
                    simplify the development process.</para>
                <para>Profiles may cover individual functional <emphasis>features</emphasis>, like
                    the aforementioned timeline but others take care of the
                        <emphasis>presentational</emphasis> aspects, like typesetting and styling.
                    Such profiles are called <emphasis>themes</emphasis>.</para>
                <para>Profiles may also aggregate and customize each other, so a profile may
                    depend on one or more other profiles. At the top of such a hierarchy sits what
                    we call a <emphasis>blueprint</emphasis>, which is essentially a ready-made configuration for a
                    complete application. Usually it will be targeting a specific use case, e.g. a
                    correspondence edition or a dictionary. In the simplest case, a blueprint may be just
                    a configuration file, which tailors the configuration of profiles it
                    uses for the specific purpose of this particular blueprint.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Continuous development</title>
                <para>TEI Publisher comes with a central application manager, Jinks, which
                    manages all profiles and the applications generated from it.</para>
                <para>Creation of an application is no longer a one-time generative step, but it can be
                    approached iteratively: new features may be added or removed, configuration for
                    the existing ones modified. The same user interface, which allowed us to select,
                    pre-configure and generate our application can be used to reconfigure and
                    regenerate it at any later point. </para>

                <para>As new profiles are added to the public library - or new versions are released
                    for the existing ones - this application manager can take care of updating
                    profiles and their dependencies used in custom applications under its control.
                    Updates can largely be carried out automatically with the number of necessary
                    manual interventions reduced to a minimum and most updates applied with a single
                    click. Gone are the days when users had to read through update
                    instructions to manually migrate to a new version of TEI Publisher. </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Basic vocabulary</title>
                <para>To clarify how various parts fit together, let us summarize some key concepts,
                    which will be used in the rest of this documentation:</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>TEI Publisher</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>denotes the software framework as a whole, i.e. the entire toolbox,
                                comprising all profiles and libraries</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Jinks</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>the central application manager, which generates applications and
                                manages updates</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>TEI Publisher Documentation and Demo</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>refers to the application containing this documentation and a
                                selection of demos. It mimics the old monolithic TEI Publisher
                                application, but is now generated from a blueprint.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Profile</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>a modular building block for a TEI Publisher application.
                                Profiles can extend other profiles and may be combined to create
                                applications. We distinguish several kinds of
                                profiles:</para>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>Base</term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>a special profile, used by all TEI Publisher
                                            applications, providing the core server-side API and
                                            basic page layout without styling</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>Feature</term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>a functional profile to be combined with base and potentially other profiles. It
                                            provides all necessary resources to fully implement a
                                            specific functional scope, e.g. docker configuration,
                                            register sidebar, or a timeline.</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>Theme</term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>provides a particular look and feel. It supplies all
                                            necessary CSS styles, fonts and graphic assets to
                                            achieve that.</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>Blueprint</term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>a complete template for an application targeted at a
                                            specific use case, e.g. a monograph, correspondence
                                            edition, dictionary etc.</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>TEI Processing Model</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>the very core of TEI Publisher. Part of the TEI Guidelines and the
                                TEI ODD specification format, it defines how documents are
                                transformed from the source XML into output formats (e.g. HTML,
                                ePub, print).</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Webcomponents</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>library of interactive custom HTML elements. These main user
                                interface building blocks of TEI Publisher can be freely combined to
                                create robust HTML pages with TEI Publisher. Part of the HTML5
                                standard and natively supported by browsers.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Jinks Templates</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>a templating language used by Jinks during application generation
                                as well as within profiles to fill placeholders with content.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="e-editiones">
            <title>e-editiones.org</title>
            <para> Since its first incarnation in 2015, TEI Publisher has gained substantial
                following with numerous academic and commercial projects around the globe, which are relying on it
                for their editorial and publishing needs. Grass-roots user initiative led in 2020 to
                the foundation of an international non-profit association <link xlink:show="new"
                    xlink:href="https://e-editiones.org">e-editiones.org</link> with the focus on
                further joint development of TEI Publisher, open standards and best practices for
                digital editions. </para>

            <para>TEI Publisher development is only possible thanks to generous contributions of
                developers, users and institutions willing to employ Open Source approaches so that
                the whole community can reuse and benefit from their work.</para>

            <para> A growing number of projects from small to large that have decided to publish
                their materials with TEI Publisher gives us all not only the opportunity but also
                the responsibility to make the project thrive for years to come and to make it truly
                sustainable option for XML publishing! Consider joining <link xlink:show="new"
                    xlink:href="https://e-editiones.org">e-editiones.org</link> through your
                affiliated institution or individually to support our efforts. </para>

            <para>We invite the community to contribute to the project – by means of code, ideas,
                documentation, tutorials and funding. </para>
            <para> You don't have to be a developer to contribute, you can do so in a number of
                ways! </para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Check out the source code, modify it, document it, enhance it.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Create new or enhance existing example documents and ODDs so we present
                        showcases for various TEI applications.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Report your issues, feature requests or ideas for discussion via <link
                            xlink:show="new"
                            xlink:href="https://github.com/eeditiones/tei-publisher-app/issues"
                            >GitHub issue tracker</link>. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Discuss with us on <link xlink:show="new"
                            xlink:href="https://join.slack.com/t/e-editiones/shared_invite/zt-e19jc03q-OFaVni~_lh6emSHen6pswg"
                            >e-editiones slack chat</link> or through the <link xlink:show="new"
                            xlink:href="https://admin.hostpoint.ch/mailman/listinfo/community_e-editiones.org"
                            >mailing list</link> and <link xlink:show="new"
                            xlink:href="https://twitter.com/EEditiones">@EEditiones twitter</link>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Contribute to translations via <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://crwd.in/tei-publisher">Crowdin</link>. Please
                        contact us if your target language is not listed and you'd like to work on
                        it. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Port back your customizations (e.g. profiles or themes) to the TEI
                        Publisher code base so that others can use it too (or ask us to do it for
                        you)! </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Help and mentor others – publish teaching materials, answer questions on
                        our Slack channel, mailing list and other forums. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Sponsor a concrete feature or fund a development grant. </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="installation">
        <title>Installation</title>
        <para>TEI Publisher requires the <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://exist-db.org"
                >eXist XML database</link> to operate. It is distributed as an eXist application
            package, making it easy to install on any eXist database instance – either on your local
            machine or any remote server. </para>
        <para> You can install eXist and TEI Publisher manually, as described below. Alternatively
            use the provided <link linkend="docker">docker image</link>. </para>

        <section xml:id="exist-installation">
            <title>Installing into an eXist instance</title>

            <section xml:id="java">
                <title>Java</title>
                <para> Before installing eXist, make sure you have Java installed on your machine.
                    You can run <command>java -version</command> on a command line to check which
                    version of Java you have. Make sure you have at least Java 8 (recommended: Java
                    11). Please note that the <command>java -version</command> shows the full
                    version string, so 1.8.0 or similar instead of just 8. </para>
                <para> If you do not have Java installed, you can choose between a variety of
                    different Java distributions for your operating system. While these are largely
                    equivalent, so far we have had the smoothest installation experience across
                    operating systems with the <link xlink:show="new"
                        xlink:href="https://www.azul.com/downloads/zulu-community/?package=jdk">Zulu
                        Community OpenJDK</link> builds. In particular for Windows users, this
                    provides the best out of the box experience. </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="download">
                <title>Download</title>

                <para> Download an eXist distribution following the link on its <link
                        xlink:show="new"
                        xlink:href="http://exist-db.org/exist/apps/homepage/index.html#downloads"
                        >homepage</link>. </para>
                <note>
                    <para>It is recommended that you set up an admin password when installing eXist
                        but make sure to remember or store it securely!</para>
                </note>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="mac-installation">
                <title>Mac installation</title>
                <para> On a Mac download the file with the <command>.dmg</command> extension, e.g. "
                        <filename> eXist-db-6.x.x.dmg</filename> ". </para>


                <para> Double clicking the downloaded <command>.dmg</command> file should install
                    eXist on your local system. It is only required to drag the eXist app icon over
                    to the Applications folder. </para>

                <para>Once the installation has completed, you should find an app in your
                    Applications folder which you can use to launch eXist.</para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="windows-installation">
                <title>Windows installation</title>
                <para> On Windows download the file with the <command>.jar</command> extension, e.g.
                    " <filename> exist-installer-6.x.x.jar</filename> ". </para>

                <para> Double clicking the <command>.jar</command> should install eXist on your
                    local system. It will launch an installer to guide you through basic settings.
                    The default settings suggested by the installer provide a good starting point
                    for most projects. </para>

                <note>
                    <para> If double-clicking the <command>.jar</command> does not have any effect,
                        there's may be something wrong with your Java setup. The
                            <filename>java</filename> binary needs to be in your
                            <envar>%PATH%</envar> environment. </para>
                    <para>You can also try to manually start the installer by opening a command
                        prompt, changing to the directory where you downloaded the distribution and
                        typing:</para>
                    <synopsis>java -jar exist-installer-6.x.x.jar</synopsis>
                </note>

                <para>Once the installation is completed, you should find an eXist-db shortcut to
                    launch eXist.</para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="unix-installation">
                <title>Unix installation</title>
                <para> Download the file with the <command>.jar</command> extension, e.g. "
                        <filename> exist-installer-6.x.x.jar</filename> ". </para>

                <para> Double clicking the <command>.jar</command> should install eXist on your
                    local system. It will launch an installer to guide you through basic settings.
                    Default settings suggested by the installer provide a good starting point for
                    most projects so there's no need to change anything. </para>

                <para> Once the installation is completed, you should find an eXist-db shortcut to
                    launch eXist, otherwise navigate to the installation directory and run
                        <command>bin/startup.sh</command>. </para>

                <note>
                    <para> Some <emphasis>Linux users</emphasis> may prefer the plain
                            <command>.tar.bz2</command> package, which can just be untarred to any
                        location. This package does not include an installer and eXist has to be
                        launched on the command line: navigate into the untarred directory and run </para>
                    <synopsis>bin/startup.sh</synopsis>
                    <para> in a shell, skipping the jar installer step above. Ignore the next
                        section, navigate directly to <link xlink:show="new"
                            xlink:href="http://localhost:8080"> http://localhost:8080</link> and
                        follow the steps for installing TEI Publisher via the dashboard described
                        further below. </para>
                </note>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="first-launch">
                <title>First launch</title>
                <para>Once eXist is launched for the first time you should see (with the exception
                    of some Unix system configurations described above) a splash window popping up,
                    showing that default applications are being installed:</para>
                <figure>
                    <title>Splash Screen on eXist Startup</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="eXistSplash.png" width="256px"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>Upon first start, an additional configuration window will pop up on Windows
                    and Mac, allowing you to configure basic parameters. Default settings suggested
                    provide a good starting point for most projects so usually there's no need to
                    change anything. </para>
                <figure>
                    <title>Configuration Dialog Showing on First Start</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="eXistInitialConfig.png" width="512px"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para> Clicking on <guibutton>Save</guibutton> will show a popup asking to confirm
                    the location of the data directory. Unless you have specific requirements just
                    agree to the suggestion of the configuration dialog. </para>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Windows users</emphasis> will be asked if they would like to install
                    eXist as a service. This is highly recommended to ensure that the database is
                    correctly closed whenever the operating system shuts down. </para>
                <para>If all went well, eXist should now be up and running in the background. Mac
                    and Windows users should find a small eXist icon in their task bar.
                    Right-clicking on it will reveal a menu:</para>
                <figure>
                    <title>Taskbar Launcher Context Menu</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="eXistTaskbarIcon.png" width="512px"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="packageManager">
                <title>Installing Jinks and TEI Publisher Documentation/Demo</title>
                <para>TEI Publisher no longer comes as a single
                    application. To get started, you need to install two packages:</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Jinks</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The central application manager from which every other application
                                is generated</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>TEI Publisher Documentation and Demo</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Contains the documentation for TEI Publisher as well as a few
                                demonstration pages for various features. This mimics the old TEI
                                Publisher application in that it allows you to explore the
                                possibilities, upload documents and experiment with ODDs. The app is
                                generated from the <emphasis>Documentation + Demo</emphasis>
                                blueprint in <productname>Jinks</productname>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
                <para>Clicking on <guimenuitem>Open Dashboard</guimenuitem> in the taskbar will open
                    a browser and display eXist's Dashboard: the central administrative hub for the
                    database. Alternatively – e.g. when you chose the manual installation on Linux –
                    you can also open a browser window and navigate to: <link xlink:show="new"
                        xlink:href="http://localhost:8080">http://localhost:8080</link>. </para>
                <para>Log into the dashboard using the admin account and the password you chose
                    during the installation (it will be empty by default). Use the left sidebar to
                    navigate to the <guimenuitem>Package Manager</guimenuitem>. You'll see two tabs:
                    the first one lists the application packages currently installed, the second can
                    be used to install additional packages from eXist's public application
                    repository.</para>
                <note>
                    <para>Should you encounter any issues with the login, try via a different app
                        (they share logins):</para>
                    <procedure>
                        <step>
                            <para>From the dashboard, open the <productname>monex</productname>
                                application.</para>
                        </step>
                        <step>
                            <para>If you are not logged in yet, this should present you with a login
                                dialog. Provide your credentials and sign in.</para>
                        </step>
                        <step>
                            <para>Go back to the <productname>dashboard</productname>. The display
                                should change and you should see the admin view.</para>
                        </step>
                    </procedure>
                </note>
                <para> Switch to the <guimenuitem>Available</guimenuitem> tab and search the list
                    for <productname>Jinks</productname>. Once you find it, click on the little
                    install icon. You can also search for TEI Publisher and install the app so you
                    can play around with the provided demos and showcases. </para>
                <para>After installing, you will find <productname>Jinks</productname> (and
                        <productname>TEI Publisher Documentation and Demo</productname>, if
                    pertinent) in the tab showing installed apps. Click on the icon to open the
                    app.</para>
                <figure>
                    <title>The Package Manager </title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="eXistDashboard.png" width="640px"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="docker">
            <title>Using docker</title>
            <para> If you do not want to install eXist yourself, you can use docker to run TEI
                Publisher. Docker is a tool to simplify the installation of applications and
                services. It creates a virtual environment including everything required for the
                service to run. Using our <link xlink:show="new"
                    xlink:href="https://hub.docker.com/r/existdb/teipublisher">docker image</link>,
                eXist will already be set up to include both Jinks and TEI
                Publisher<!-- as well as the... TODO: add here any demos that will also be included -->. </para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para> Install <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://www.docker.com/"
                            >docker</link> on your machine. Windows and Mac users may download the
                            <link xlink:show="new"
                            xlink:href="https://www.docker.com/products/docker-desktop">docker
                            desktop</link> app. </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To download the image run the following in a console</para>
                    <synopsis>docker pull existdb/teipublisher:latest</synopsis>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>once the download is complete, you can run the image with the following
                        command:</para>
                    <synopsis>docker run -p 8081:8080 -p 8444:8443 --name teipublisher existdb/teipublisher:latest</synopsis>
                    <para>Startup should be fast because the database is already pre-populated.
                        However, changes you make may not persist if the docker container is deleted
                        or updated to a newer release. If you want to be sure that your changes are
                        safe, you should specify a local volume for storing the database by
                        adding:</para>
                    <synopsis>-v exist-data:/exist/data</synopsis>
                    <para>See below for an explanation of the parameters:</para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term>-p</term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Maps a port on your local machine (8081 and 8444) to the port
                                    used by eXist within the container. eXist will always run on
                                    8080 for HTTP and 8443 for HTTPS. If those ports are already
                                    occupied by different services on your machine, choose a
                                    different port for the first number.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term>-v</term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para> Creates a named ("exist-data") volume for storing the
                                    database, using the directory specified after the colon. If you
                                    skip this, any changes to the database will be lost if you
                                    remove the docker container, update it or create a new one. With
                                        <option>-v</option> the data will be stored outside the
                                    container. </para>
                                <para>If you just intend to play around a bit, you can skip the
                                    parameter.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term>--name</term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para> Assigns a name to the container, so you can reference it in
                                    other docker commands, like <code>docker stop</code>. We'll use
                                    the name in all commands below. </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                    <para>Once the container has started, you can access the eXist dashboard in your
                        browser by navigating to</para>
                    <synopsis>http://localhost:8081</synopsis>
                    <para>From the dashboard you can click on the TEI Publisher, Shakespeare or Van
                        Gogh icons to open the corresponding applications.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To stop the container run</para>
                    <synopsis>docker stop teipublisher</synopsis>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To start the container again:</para>
                    <synopsis>docker start teipublisher</synopsis>
                    <para>Note that when you restart a container, it will run in detached mode, so
                        you won't see any console output. You can view the output with following
                        command though:</para>
                    <synopsis>docker logs teipublisher</synopsis>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <section xml:id="docker-other">
                <title>Other useful commands</title>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>docker container ps -a</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Lists all running and stopped containers</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>docker volume ls</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Displays existing volumes (where your database is stored)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>docker cp teipublisher:/exist-data .</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Copy the contents of the database data volume to the current
                                directory on local disk, so you can back it up. Note that this will
                                copy the raw database files as created by eXist (not your XML, which
                                is binary encoded inside those files). Also make sure you run the
                                command after stopping the active container.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>docker volume rm exist-data</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Remove the contents of the database data volume (in case you would
                                like to start from scratch, deleting all changes you made).</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>

                <para> Have a look at the docker documentation and <link xlink:show="new"
                        xlink:href="https://www.docker.com/sites/default/files/Docker_CheatSheet_08.09.2016_0.pdf"
                        > cheatsheet</link> for more commands. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="tp">
        <title>Guided Tour</title>
        <para>For a first overview we recommend to start with the <productname>TEI Publisher
                Documentation and Demo</productname> application. This includes the documentation,
            provides a few selected demos, and also allows you to upload your own documents to the
                <filename>demo</filename> collection as well as to play around with different ODDs
            or create your own.</para>
        <note>
            <para>The <productname>TEI Publisher Documentation and
                    Demo</productname> app corresponds to one of the pre-configured blueprints
                available in Jinks, which you'll find under the name <guimenuitem>Documentation +
                    Demo</guimenuitem> on the <guimenuitem>Profiles</guimenuitem> tab in Jinks.
            </para>
        </note>
        <section xml:id="browsing">
            <title>Browsing Documents</title>
            <section xml:id="start-page">
                <title>The Start Page</title>
                <para>The start page of <productname>TEI Publisher Documentation and
                        Demo</productname> serves as an entry point to explore and
                    experiment.</para>
                <para>The left side panel presents search and filtering options. The central panel
                    lists the available collections or – if you browse into a collection – the
                    documents within. Another panel to the right shows the list of ODD files
                    provided by the app.</para>

                <figure>
                    <title>First options in the start page collection listing</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="start-page-collections.png" width="512px"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>The usual starting point is the <emphasis role="bold">Demo
                        Collection</emphasis> with which users can explore a range of <link
                        linkend="selected-use-cases">selected use cases</link>, demonstrating
                    various genres, encoding styles and presentation layouts. Various customization
                    aspects are handled using different ODDs and view templates. We suggest to have
                    a look at each of them to see what TEI Publisher can achieve out of the
                    box.</para>
            </section>         
        </section>
        <section xml:id="selected-use-cases">
            <title>Selected Use Cases</title>
            <para>The document view can vary, sometimes substantially, depending on the sample
                document you are looking at. This is a natural consequence of TEI's versatility and
                broad scope of its application. What follows, requirements for the document view –
                both its layout and composition as well as processing rules governing the
                transformation of the text of the document itself – will differ to a great extent.
                Sample documents which are included in TEI Publisher's installation package do not
                exhaust its applications but rather aim to present some chosen use cases:</para>
                <figure>
                    <title>Browsing Demo collection</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="demo-collection-overview.png" width="512px"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Critik der reinen Vernunft</emphasis> from the <emphasis>Deutsches
                            Textarchiv</emphasis> corpus presents a philosophical tractate,
                        originally published in print, thus following 'traditional' book structure
                        with front pages, foreword and chapters. It can nevertheless demonstrate
                        very well Publisher's capacities in typesetting, switching between physical
                        and logical structure of the document (just toggle <guibutton>Page
                            View</guibutton> in the <guibutton>Settings</guibutton> panel) as well
                        as generation of multiple output formats from single set of processing
                        models in the ODD (try choosing <parameter>PDF</parameter> or
                            <parameter>ePub</parameter> options in the
                            <guibutton>Download</guibutton>). <emphasis>Purchas his
                            pilgrimages</emphasis>, from the <emphasis>EEBO-TCP</emphasis> project,
                        while roughly similar in structure is much earlier work (1613) and
                        demonstrates extensive use of marginal notes. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Shakespeare's <emphasis>Romeo and Juliet</emphasis>, from
                            <emphasis>Bodleian First Folio</emphasis> project uses dedicated TEI
                        elements to encode structure of the play but it also showcases the parallel
                        transcription and facsimile alignment for its presentation which is
                        obviously of general application and could be used for any genre, not
                        limited to dramatic texts. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Correspondence corpora are common, yet very interesting, subjects for
                        digital editions. Despite basic similarities in structure, depending on the
                        period, scope and particular research perspective, intended presentation may
                        vary enormously. We are presenting samples of:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> A 16th century manuscript letter of <emphasis role="bold">Hernán
                                    Cortés</emphasis> showcasing parallel transcription/translation
                                and facsimile view and transcription enhanced with commentaries and
                                explicitly encoded transcriptional features.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> A letter from <emphasis role="bold">Van Gogh</emphasis> to Paul
                                Gauguin written in 1888. This intentionally reproduces the flexible
                                column layout pioneered by the <link xlink:show="new"
                                    xlink:href="http://vangoghletters.org">Vincent Van Gogh
                                    Letters</link> online edition, which is a model example for
                                correspondence.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>For a taste of completely different encoding style we present several 19th
                        century lexicons and dictionaries:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> A manuscript collocative dictionary of Polish <emphasis
                                    role="bold">Bogactwa mowy polskiej</emphasis> featuring
                                interactive highlights for regions of interest of the facsimile when
                                hovering over dictionary headwords. Internal composition is based on
                                the <code>entryFree</code> element with a rich
                                microstructure.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> An encyclopedia of philosophic terms by Friedrich Kirchner and
                                Carl Michaëlis, published in 1907: <emphasis>Wörterbuch der
                                    Philosophischen Grundbegriffe</emphasis>. This is based on the
                                Lex-0 customization of TEI and provides a sidebar to browse the
                                available lemmata.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        
            <note>
                <title>Note</title>
                <para>You may notice that the list of included samples is more limited than in version
                    9. Some examples have been moved into separate profiles (see the
                        <emphasis>Serafin</emphasis> blueprint for a correspondence edition), the
                    rest has been condensed and streamlined. The base ODD now covers many more TEI
                    features out of the box, so fewer samples are necessary.</para>
                <para>We'd like to stress that preparing showcases above has been only possible
                    thanks to numerous projects releasing their sources openly, in particular the
                        <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://firstfolio.bodleian.ox.ac.uk"
                        >Bodleian First Folio</link>, <link xlink:show="new"
                        xlink:href="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de">Deutsches Textarchiv</link>,
                        <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://vangoghletters.org">Vincent Van
                        Gogh Museum</link> and <link xlink:show="new"
                        xlink:href="https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/tcp-eebo">
                        EEBO-TCP</link>. We'd also like to thank William Graves and Anna Skolimowska
                    for sharing their correspondence material. </para>
            </note>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="odd-experiments">
            <title>Experimenting with ODDs</title>
            <para>All TEI Publisher's sample documents are XML files which are transformed into a
                HTML webpage for display in the browser. Several factors determine how the final
                page is going to look like: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the ODD used for transforming the TEI XML into HTML for the content</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the HTML page templates being used for the overall structure and layout of
                        the page</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>various functional blocks contributed by profiles (register sidebars,
                        facsimile viewer …)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>All dynamic parts of the page, i.e. the text display, navigation buttons
                        etc., are defined as small, reusable blocks, using the Web Components
                        technology. Components can be used like common HTML elements.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>We have already mentioned in the very first section that the TEI Processing Model
                lies at the heart of the Publisher – the ODD file associated with a document defines
                the rules of transformation of the XML source file into HTML. Detailed discussion of
                the Processing Model can be found in the <link
                    xlink:href="documentation.xml?id=pm-syntax">reference manual</link>, for now it
                is sufficient to say this is where decisions if a TEI element should be rendered
                inline, with a tooltip, or as a marginal note, are made. Simplifying things a bit,
                the <emphasis>text</emphasis> of the document that you see rendered in your browser
                is an effect of applying the rules from ODD file to the source document. When
                opening a document of the Demo collection, it is possible to see in the URL the
                    <parameter>odd</parameter> parameter indicating which ODD file is being used to
                process the document, e.g. <link xlink:href="../demo/F-rom.xml?odd=shakespeare"
                    >demo/F-rom.xml?odd=shakespeare</link>.</para>
            <para>Most demos come with their own ODD. However, all of them – at least if they deal
                with TEI – extend the base ODD, <filename>teipublisher.odd</filename>.</para>
            <para>Nevertheless, as we demonstrated in the section on selected sample documents, in
                the application context we certainly want more than just text, however nicely
                typeset. From basic navigation controls, table of content, to facsimile display,
                critical apparatus, glossaries and maps – all of this and much more could be
                included in the final webpage.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="upload">
            <title>Uploading documents</title>
            <para> If you are reading this, you may already have some documents 
            you might want published, whether they are in TEI, DocBook, JATS, MS Word
                DOCX or other XML format. The <productname>Documentation and Demo</productname>
                application allows you to upload documents into the <guilabel>Demo
                    Collection</guilabel>. The first step is to upload them into the database, for
                which you need to be <emphasis role="bold">logged in</emphasis>. The user and
                password are displayed in the information block on top of the right sidebar.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>The Upload Panel</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="upload.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Upon successful login, uploading is just a question of dragging your documents
                onto the <guibutton>Upload</guibutton> area. They will become available in the
                document list immediately after upload is successfully completed. The upload panel 
                will also display the upload results. In case of problems, very often resulting from not well-formed XML, you will see a warning message.</para>
            <para>Now you can view your documents! The transformation will use the 
                rules of the base ODD. For
                most text-centric TEI, the default rendition should already produce a readable
                result, but you will likely find aspects to improve to match your expectations. Quite often the need for
                customization will be limited to just a handful of elements. Refer to <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="documentation.xml?id=odd-customization">TEI Processing Model transformations</link> chapter to learn about the ODDs and the Processing Model.</para>
            <para>If you upload a Microsoft Word document, the upload will automatically
                trigger the conversion of Word to TEI, using a special ODD for the tranformation.
                Please note that the focus of this conversion is to preserve textual content,
                structure and basic semantics of the text, not to provide authoritative mapping of
                complete set of MS Word features to TEI. Refer to <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="documentation.xml?id=docx">DOCX
                    handling</link> section for more information. </para>
        </section>

    </section>
    <section xml:id="using-jinks">
        <title>Hands-on with Jinks</title>
        <para>After playing around with the <productname>TEI Publisher Documentation and
                Demo</productname> application, let's try and generate your own custom edition.
            As explained above, TEI Publisher now has an application manager, called
                <productname>Jinks</productname>. This will be your main entry point for creating or
            updating a custom edition.</para>
        <para>You can access <productname>Jinks</productname> via
                <productname>eXist-db's</productname> Dashboard. If you have not installed
                <productname>Jinks</productname> yet, use the Package Manager in the Dashboard to do
            so.</para>
        <para>Opening Jinks for the first time, you'll see the main administration page with three
            columns: the sidebar to the left shows the list of installed applications which were
            created with Jinks (if any). The central column contains the main configuration form
            with several tabs. The right column presents the configuration, as is currently in effect
            for the application. The configuration is in JSON format and will initially show as an
            empty object (empty curly brackets). As you fill out the form, you'll see how the JSON
            configuration is populated with corresponding entries.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Jinks with basic config</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="jinks-config.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <section xml:id="using-jinks-first-steps">
            <title>First Steps</title>
            <para>To start, you must fill at least the top three input
                fields under the first tab, <guilabel>Application Configuration</guilabel>. 
                In the first box, <guilabel>Abbreviation</guilabel>, provide a short but unique name. 
                It will serve as a collection name in the database, where the application is stored. 
                </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">NB:</emphasis>Abbreviation may not contain whitespace,
                brackets and special characters. It may only contain alphanumeric characters
                (letters and numbers) supplemented with dashes (-) and underscore (_). </para>
            <para>After filling out the abbreviation field, suggestions for the following two text boxes
               are provided automatically. The
                    <option>label</option> is the title of the application, and will be used to caption the app in the Dashboard and elsewhere.
                    It will initially be the set the same as the abbreviation,
                but you may change it to be more descriptive - and you can freely use whitespace, brackets etc. The <option>unique identifier</option>
                must be a URI, but it does not need to be a real URL, pointing to some existing
                website. Like a namespace in XML, it can be anything as long as it is syntactically
                valid and unique.</para>
            <para>Running the generator with just these settings, the result would be an
              application without any documents. To provide some data to test with, switch to
                the <guilabel>Profiles</guilabel> tab, search for the <guilabel>Demo Data</guilabel>
                feature in the <guilabel>Data Packages</guilabel> subsection and enable that
                checkbox.</para>
            <para>You are now ready to run the generator for the first time: click on the
                    <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button in the bottom toolbar of
                    <productname>Jinks</productname>. You'll see a wait indicator appear next to the
                button. The process may take a while as it
                consists of multiple steps:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>configurations of all selected profiles are merged</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>files supplied by each profile are copied into a temporary collection in
                        the database</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>the temporary collection is packaged and installed into eXist-db</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <para>Once the application is installed, a dialog will open. If you are creating a new app,
                it will inform you that the package has been deployed, along with a link which
                you can click to open the newly created application.</para>
            <para>If you followed this section to the letter, and added only the <guilabel>Demo Data</guilabel>
                feature, the created application should present three sermons by theologician Karl
                Barth. Clicking on one of those will display the text of the sermon.</para>

        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adding Features</title>
            <para>The sermons contain mentions of places and people. To make use of the information available about
                these in the dataset, we can enable the profile dedicated to that very purpose.</para>
                <para>Switch back to <productname>Jinks</productname>, go to the
                    <guilabel>Profiles</guilabel> tab and find the <guilabel>Entity
                    Registers</guilabel> profile in the <guilabel>Features</guilabel> category.
                Enable it and click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> again.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Jinks profiles tab</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="jinks-profiles.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The <guilabel>Command Output</guilabel> dialog will now present a list of files
                which were updated. Close it and return to the generated app. Looking at the
                menubar, you will notice that there are new menu items for
                    <guilabel>People</guilabel> and <guilabel>Places</guilabel>, leading to separate
                pages for browsing those entities.</para>
            <para>We might also like to show a list of places and people mentioned in the current
                document, when viewing one of the sermons. This sub-feature is not enabled by default,
                because editions may want to limit it to some pages.</para>
            <para>To enable it globally, go back to Jinks and look at the editor to the right, which
                shows you a JSON representation of the currently active configuration for the
                application. Right now it should look like this (though the order of properties may
                differ):</para>
            <programlisting language="json">{
  "pkg": {
    "abbrev": "mytest"
  },
  "label": "mytest",
  "id": "https://e-editiones.org/apps/mytest",
  "extends": [
    "base10",
    "demo-data",
    "registers",
    "theme-base10"
  ]
}</programlisting>
            <para>Configuration parameters for feature profiles must go under a
                property called <code>features</code>, followed by the name of the profile. While we're
                at it, we could also disable the navigation buttons in the toolbar (the sermons use
                a single-page display). Change the configuration and add the <code>features</code> as
                below:</para>
            <programlisting language="json">{
  "pkg": {
    "abbrev": "mytest"
  },
  "label": "mytest",
  "id": "https://e-editiones.org/apps/mytest",
  "extends": [
    "base10",
    "demo-data",
    "registers",
    "theme-base10"
  ],
  "features": {
    "register": {
        "enabled": true
    },
    "toolbar": {
      "navigation": false
    }
  }
}</programlisting>
            <para>After applying the new configuration, you should find a register sidebar, listing people and places, to the
                right of each sermon's text.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Document view with register sidebar</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="jinks-registers.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Customizing the theme</title>
            <para>Some of the most frequently changed styling aspects can be configured via the
                    <filename>config.json</filename>, allowing users to change colors, fonts or
                logos without editing CSS. For example, most projects will want to use their own logo
                in the menu and the splash screen (which appears while a page loads), and
                perhaps pick a custom background for the header as well.</para>
            <para>To make these changes, we first have to upload the necessary images. The
                    <guilabel>Files</guilabel> tab in <productname>Jinks</productname> provides a
                simple file manager, which we can use to browse and upload files into the database.
                It will initially show the collection root of the currently selected application.
                Images used for the general page layout should go into
                    <filename>resources/images</filename>, so navigate to that collection, then
                either drag and drop the desired images from your system's file manager or click the
                    <guibutton>Upload</guibutton> button.</para>
            <note>
                <para>The <guilabel>Files</guilabel> tab will only become visible after you
                    generated the application!</para>
            </note>
            <figure>
                <title>Jinks: Managing Files</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="jinks-filemanager.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>With the images uploaded, we can add them to the configuration.
                All settings related to the look and feel of an application go into the
                    <code>"theme"</code> property of the config. For example, to change the logo,
                splash screen image and menubar background, we could change the configuration as
                follows:</para>
            <programlisting language="json"><![CDATA[{
  "pkg": {
    "abbrev": "mytest"
  },
  "label": "mytest",
  "id": "https://e-editiones.org/apps/mytest",
  "extends": [
    "base10",
    "demo-data",
    "registers",
    "theme-base10"
  ],
  "features": {
    "register": {
        "enabled": true
    },
    "toolbar": {
      "navigation": false
    }
  },
  "theme": {
    "logo": {
      "image": "../images/logo-white.png"
    },
    "menubar": {
      "background-image": "../images/type.jpeg"
    },
    "splash": {
      "image": "../images/Karl_Barth.jpg"
    },
    "fonts": {
      "content": {
        "family": "var(--jinks-base-font-family)",
        "size": "1.125rem"
      }
    }
  }
}]]></programlisting>
            <para>Note that all image paths will be relative to the CSS stylesheet (which lives in
                    <filename>resources/css</filename>), so we have to go up one level (using
                    <filename>../</filename>) and then down to <filename>images</filename>.</para>
            <para>The final setting above also changes the font used for the content. By default
                this will be a serif font (<productname>JunicodeVF</productname>), which is good for
                many historic scripts, but for a 20th century text, we may prefer to use the same
                sans-serif font as for the rest of the page (<productname>Inter</productname>).
                However, instead of providing a font name directly, we reference the CSS variable
                    <code>--jinks-base-font-family</code>, which predefines the corresponding
                font.</para>
            <para>We may want to decrease the font size a bit as well, setting it to
                    <code>1.125rem</code>. Note that for font scaling to work properly, we should
                use relative sizes based on the browser's base size, therefore using <code>rem</code>
                here, not sizes in points or pixels.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>App with theme changes applied</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="karl-barth-theme.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Finally, we can change the color scheme used by switching to the
                    <guilabel>Theming</guilabel> tab and choosing one of the available schemes. Note
                that this will add a property <code>"palette"</code> to the configuration,
                referencing the selected color scheme's name. </para>
            <note>
                <para>TEI Publisher comes with a small number of predefined color schemes, but you can add your own palette. 
                Using a well-chosen, limited color palette is in general considered good practice in web design, which is why we avoid
                    using hardcoded colors.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Customizing the ODD</title>
            <para>And now: action! One important step is still missing for a custom edition: creating your own ODD
                for text transformations. Jinks provides a control for this on the
                    <guilabel>Application Configuration</guilabel> tab. Since we're dealing with
                Karl Barth, let's add an ODD called <filename>barth.odd</filename>.</para>
            <para>After clicking <guibutton>Add</guibutton>, you'll see two new configuration
                entries:</para>
            <programlisting language="json">"odds": [
    "barth.odd"
  ],
  "defaults": {
    "odd": "barth.odd"
  }</programlisting>
            <para>The first adds <filename>barth.odd</filename> to the list of available ODDs
                inherited from the base and other profiles. The second sets this ODD as the default
                to use.</para>
            <note>
                <para>The created ODD will be empty, but extends
                        <filename>teipublisher.odd</filename>. If you would like to register an ODD
                    you already have, use the file manager to copy it to
                        <filename>resources/odd</filename> first. Afterwards follow the same steps
                    as described here. Jinks will notice that the file already exists and will just
                    register it.</para>
            </note>
            <para>What is important to know now is that adding an ODD to the configuration
                    <emphasis>after</emphasis> the app was initially generated <emphasis>does not
                    automatically use this ODD</emphasis>. Very likely the text will still be
                rendered using the default <filename>teipublisher.odd</filename>, which is the
                fallback.</para>
            <para>To fix this we need to run an action one time: actions are shown in the bottom
                toolbar of <productname>Jinks</productname>. Each profile may contribute its own
                actions, but there are four default actions always available. One of them is called
                    <guilabel>Fix ODDs</guilabel>. Click on it to recompile all ODDs (which means to
                translate them into XQuery code) and wire them up correctly in the system. Once the
                process has completed, the new ODD will actually be used and you could start
                extending it.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Jinks action toolbar</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="jinks-action-toolbar.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <note>
                <para>You only need the <guilabel>Fix ODDs</guilabel> action if you add or update an ODD in an
                    already existing application, i.e. an application already installed into the
                    database – or if there were <emphasis>upstream updates</emphasis> to the
                    profiles you use (see the section on appying updates below).</para>
                <para>The same goes for the <guilabel>Reindex Data</guilabel> action: you only need
                    to call it, if you changed the index configuration for an existing app.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Downloading the application</title>
            <para>
                <productname>Jinks</productname> operates within the database, which means all
                files it generates and modifies exist inside the database only. To keep track of changes and to have a backup, 
                you always want to download the generated files to the filesystem. There are
                two actions for this:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><guilabel>Download</guilabel></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Packages the application into a single archive (a so called XAR),
                            which you can later re-install into eXist-db using the Package Manager
                            in the Dashboard. This is a quick choice for passing the application on to other people to try out.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><guilabel>Sync</guilabel></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Synchronizes the file hierarchy into a local disk directory. Note that
                                <emphasis>local</emphasis> means the machine where eXist-db is
                            running. If you are using docker, the directory will be
                                <emphasis>inside</emphasis> the docker image. If you connect to a
                            remote server, it will be a directory on the server. Sync
                            therefore is particularly convenient to use during the development, to create snapshots 
                            to be committed to the source control repository, like Git.
                            </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>Which option to choose depends on your development workflow. Some people prefer to
                do all development inside the database and only sync or download every now and then.
                This does not require any additional setup. </para>
            <para>However, experienced developers would usually do it the other way around: have the
                code on the file system in a directory connected to Git, and do the main development
                there. This way you can make sure you'll always be able to restore the previous
                state, even if the database crashes, your computer breaks, customization attempt goes sideways or whatever bad may
                happen.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Applying updates</title>
            <para>There are two main scenarios in which you will update the application via Jinks (by
                pressing the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button):</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>you modified the configuration: by changing settings,
                        adding/removing profiles, uploading new files etc. This is what we've done
                        above.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a new version of TEI Publisher becomes available, which means you will
                        update the version of Jinks installed, and – as a consequence – some of the
                        profiles your app is using will have changed
                        <emphasis>upstream</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>
                <productname>Jinks</productname> continuously tracks the files in your application
                to make sure updates will run smoothly. In particular, it needs to prevent that
                    <emphasis>upstream updates</emphasis>, i.e. changes coming from a profile, will
                overwrite any change you have applied locally in your app.</para>
            <para>Whenever you press <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>, the <guilabel>Command
                    Output</guilabel> dialog will show you a list of files. To the left of each file
                you'll see a label. In most cases (hopefully) this should show "update" with a green
                background. However, there might also be read labels static "conflict" next to some
                files.</para>
            <figure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="jinks-conflict.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>A "conflict" means that <productname>Jinks</productname> detected changes you made
                to this file since it was last updated, and it refused to overwrite this file with
                the original version coming from one of the profiles. For example, if I would change
                    <filename>teipublisher.odd</filename> in my app (via the ODD editor), Jinks
                would detect this next time I press <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> and mark it as a
                conflict.</para>
            <para>It will be up to you to decide how to handle the conflict. If it was introduced by
                mistake, you can tell <productname>Jinks</productname> to ignore the conflict and
                overwrite the file with the upstream version by clicking the <guilabel>Overwrite
                    with next update</guilabel> button to the right of the entry. You may also
                decide that the change is valid, meaning that the conflict is expected and you'll
                not do anything about it.</para>
            <note>
                <para>To avoid conflicts it is important that most of your changes go into files you
                    have added yourself. On many levels TEI Publisher 10 provides configuration
                    options, which allow you to add custom CSS stylesheets, javascript, or API
                    endpoints to your application without changing what is already there. Those
                    added custom files will never trigger a conflict, because they only exist within
                    your application.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Operation modes</title>
            <para>Tightly connected to updates and conflict detection are the three different
                operation modes <productname>Jinks</productname> provides. You can switch between
                them through the select on the bottom of the <guilabel>Application
                    Configuration</guilabel> tab:<variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><guilabel>Quick update</guilabel></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>is the fastest mode and selected by default. It does not check
                                every file for changes, but looks at the last modification date to
                                see if there were changes to the <emphasis>upstream
                                    version</emphasis> coming from the profile.</para>
                            <para>Consequently it will not report conflicts if they can be safely
                                ignored (because there are no upstream changes to overwrite
                                them).</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><guilabel>All</guilabel></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>checks the content of each file and compares it to the version
                                last installed. This mode reliably detects and reports all potential
                                conflicts.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><guilabel>Factory reset</guilabel></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>is the most drastic and dangerous of the modes: it completely
                                deletes the installed application and recreates everything from the
                                configuration. <emphasis>Don't use it unless you you have the current version safely 
                                backed up and really know what you are doing: 
                                you are certain you want to start from scratch, or you are a developer
                                    working on a profile for Jinks</emphasis>!</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>
        </section>
        
    </section>
    <section xml:id="next">
            <title>Further steps</title>
            <para>This brief introduction aims to give a very basic orientation in using Jinks and TEI Publisher. For more in depth discussion of various subjects you may want to check the <link xlink:href="documentation.xml">Reference Manual</link> and <link xlink:href="webcomponents.xml">Web Components</link>.</para>
            <para>e-editiones runs a series of monthly community meetups and also maintans a Slack community, which provide a space for discussion, coordination of efforts and community support. Check the <link xlink:href="https://www.e-editiones.org">website</link> to find meeting announcements and recordings of past presentations and workshops.</para>
        </section>
</article>