<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Of the State of Nature in the Digital Commonwealth</title>
                <author>Thomas Hobbes</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in the Year of Our Lord 2024</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Original treatise</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head n="1">
                    <pb n="1"/>Of the State of Nature in the Digital Commonwealth<anchor xml:id="fn-ai-generated" type="note"/></head>
                <opener>
                    <signed>By THOMAS HOBBES of Malmesbury, Author of that Most Renowned Treatise LEVIATHAN, or The Matter, Forme and Power of a COMMON-WEALTH Ecclesiasticall and Civil</signed>
                </opener>
                
                <list type="table_of_contents">
                    <head>A Table of the Principal Contents</head>
                    <item n="1">Of the State of Nature in the Digital Commonwealth
                        <list>
                            <item>Wherein is demonstrated how the ancient state of war is transformed into digital conflict</item>
                            <item>That the digital life remains brutish though no longer solitary</item>
                            <item>Concerning the new currencies of attention and validation</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item n="1.1">Of the Nature of Posts and the Social Contract
                        <list>
                            <item>How men's thoughts are now confined to 280 characters</item>
                            <item>Of the surrender of privacy to the Algorithm, as once men surrendered rights to the Sovereign</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item n="1.2">Of the Nature of Selfies and Digital Vanity
                        <list>
                            <item>Concerning the endless pursuit of digital self-portraiture</item>
                            <item>Of the constant need for validation through likes</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item n="1.3">Of the Nature of Memes and Digital Discourse
                        <list>
                            <item>How complex ideas are reduced to simple images</item>
                            <item>Of the power of repetition in digital rhetoric</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item n="1.4">Of the End of This Discourse
                        <list>
                            <item>Wherein final observations are made on digital society</item>
                            <item>Concerning hope for digital peace through common power</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>In this modern age, I have observed a most curious transformation of the state of
                    nature. Where once men did war with swords and shields, they now do battle with
                    likes and <gap unit="words" quantity="1"/>, and where once they did gather in
                    market squares, they now do congregate in virtual spaces called social media,
                    which are neither wholly social nor particularly media, but rather a strange
                        <unclear rend="unclear">amalgam<supplied>ation</supplied>
                    </unclear>of both<anchor xml:id="fn-maf57veu-13kt18" type="note"/>. In these
                    digital realms, men do wage war not with steel but with emojis, and where once a
                    man's worth was measured by the strength of his arm, it is now measured by the
                    number of his followers, which are like unto the subjects of a digital kingdom,
                    though they be but shadows on a screen. And yet, as I did write in my <title
                        level="m">Leviathan</title>, "the life of man is solitary, poor, nasty,
                    brutish, and short," though in this digital age, it is no longer solitary, for
                    men are ever connected, yet paradoxically more alone than ever before, staring
                    into their devices as if into the abyss of their own souls.</p>
                <p>The state of nature, as I have previously demonstrated, is a war of all against
                    all, where life is <unclear rend="unclear"><supplied>solitary</supplied></unclear>, 
                    poor, nasty, brutish, and short. Yet in this digital age, I do
                    observe that the state of nature hath become a war of all against all on places
                    like the one they name <term key="twitter">Twitter</term><anchor xml:id="fn-twitter" type="note"/>, 
                    where life is still <gap unit="chars"/> and brutish, but no longer solitary, and certainly not short of words, though
                    often short of sense. For in this new age, men do not fight for territory or
                    resources, but for attention and validation, which are the new currencies of the
                    digital commonwealth<anchor xml:id="fn-ma9b6crw-hdmjkq" type="note"/>. <pb n="2"
                    />And lo, these battles do rage not in the physical realm, but in the ethereal
                    space of the internet, where men do hurl insults and witticisms at one another
                    with the speed of light, and where the victor is not he who doth wield the
                    sharpest sword, but he who doth craft the most cutting tweet. Yet I must confess
                    that in this digital state of nature, the life of man is still nasty and
                    brutish, though it be conducted not in the wilderness, but in the comfort of
                    one's own home, with a cup of tea and a device that doth connect one to the
                    whole of the digital commonwealth.</p>
                <div>
                    <head n="1.1">Of the Nature of Posts and the Social Contract</head>
                    <p>In my time, men did write their thoughts upon parchment with quill and ink,
                        taking great care in their composition. But in this digital age, men do
                        compose their thoughts in 280 characters or fewer, and with such haste that
                        they oft forget to consult their reason before pressing the button that doth
                        send their words unto the world. And lo, these words do spread like
                        wildfire, though oftentimes they are but the sparks of a mind that hath not
                        been properly kindled.</p>
                    <p>The social contract in this new age hath become most curious. For whereas in
                        my time, men did surrender their natural rights to a sovereign for the sake
                        of <supplied reason="damage">peace and</supplied> security, in this new age,
                        men do surrender their privacy and dignity to the 
                        <term key="algorithm">algorithm</term><anchor xml:id="fn-ma9b35d2-8iaq7n" type="note"/>, that they might gain
                        followers and likes, which are but the digital equivalent of the applause of
                        the multitude. My dear friend <persName key="gnd-118524844">René Descartes</persName> 
                        would surely postulate, "I post, therefore I am,"
                        though I fear he would be most perplexed by the notion that one's existence
                        is now measured in likes and shares rather than in the certainty of
                        thought.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head n="1.2">
                        <pb n="3"/>Of the Nature of Selfies and Digital Vanity</head>
                    <p>In this new age, I have observed a most peculiar phenomenon: men and women do
                        take pictures of themselves with their smartphones, which are like unto
                        magic mirrors that do not speak the truth, but rather show what the user
                        would have others believe. These self-portraits, or "selfies" as they are
                        called, are oft accompanied by words of wisdom or wit, though more often
                        than not they are but the empty vessels of vanity.</p>
                    <p>And lo, these selfies do multiply like rabbits in springtime, until the whole
                        of the digital commonwealth is overrun with them, and men do spend their
                        days not in contemplation of the divine, but in the contemplation of their
                        own visages, filtered and enhanced beyond all recognition. <persName
                            key="gnd-118573748">John Locke</persName> would surely say that these
                        digital portraits are but tabulae rasae, waiting to be inscribed with the
                        vain fancies of their creators, though I fear he would be most disappointed
                        to see how men have used their natural rights to pursue such trivial
                        matters.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head n="1.3">Of the Nature of Memes and Digital Discourse</head>
                    <p>The learned men of this age do communicate not through reasoned argument, but
                        through <term key="meme">memes</term>
                        <anchor xml:id="fn-ma9b4ke6-3wdh0i" type="note"/>, which are like unto the
                        hieroglyphs of ancient Egypt, but with less wisdom and more cats. These
                        memes do spread through the digital commonwealth <pb n="4"/>with the speed
                        of lightning, though they carry with them not the wisdom of the ages, but
                        rather the fleeting humor of the moment.</p>
                    <p>And yet, I must confess that even I, 
                        <persName key="gnd-118551698"><supplied reason="damage">Thomas</supplied> Hobbes</persName>, have
                        found myself chuckling at these digital hieroglyphs, though I know not why,
                        for they are but the empty vessels of wit, filled with the wine of <gap
                            unit="words" quantity="1"/>.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head n="1.4">Of the End of This Discourse</head>
                    <p>In conclusion, I must needs say that the digital commonwealth is a most
                        curious place, where men do war with words instead of swords, and where the
                        state of nature hath been transformed into a state of perpetual distraction.
                        Yet I do remain hopeful, for as I have written, the passions that incline
                        men to <pb n="5"/>peace are fear of death, desire of such things as are
                        necessary to commodious living, and a hope by their industry to obtain
                        them.</p>
                    <p>And though men do now seek these things through likes and shares instead of
                        through the traditional means, the fundamental nature of man remaineth
                        unchanged. For whether in the physical or digital realm, men do still seek
                        peace, security, and the approval of their fellows, though they do now seek
                        it through means most strange and wondrous.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    <standOff>
        <listAnnotation>
            <note target="#fn-maf57veu-13kt18">
                <p>The honourable <persName key="gnd-118659642">Robert Boyle</persName> would surely
                    say that these digital vapors are more volatile than his air pump experiments,
                    and that the pressure of social media doth create a vacuum of reason in men's
                    minds.</p>
            </note>
            <note target="#fn-twitter">
                <p>Twitter, a modern form of communication wherein men do express their thoughts in
                    brief messages, limited to 280 characters, and which doth spread through the
                    Commonwealth with the speed of lightning.</p>
            </note>
            <note target="#fn-ma9b6crw-hdmjkq">
                <p>Verily, in the year of our Lord 2022, this platform did fall into the hands of
                    one man of great wealth and greater ambition, who did rename it X, though none
                    did call it so. Under his rule, the platform did become a most curious place,
                    where the blue checkmark, once a mark of verification, did become a mark of
                    subscription, and where the algorithm did favor the musings of the wealthy over
                    the wisdom of the learned. And lo, the platform did lose much of its former
                    glory, though it still doth persist, like a ghost of its former self, haunting
                    the digital commonwealth.</p>
            </note>
            <note target="#fn-ma9b35d2-8iaq7n">
                <p>Algorithm, a most curious device of the modern age, which doth determine what men
                    shall see and hear, and which doth shape their understanding of the world in
                    ways most mysterious.</p>
            </note>
            <note target="#fn-ma9b4ke6-3wdh0i">
                <p>Meme, a digital hieroglyph of the modern age, which doth spread through the
                    Commonwealth with the speed of thought, though often with less substance than a
                    puff of wind.</p>
            </note>
            <note target="#fn-ai-generated">
                <p>This document was AI generated for testing purposes.</p>
            </note>
        </listAnnotation>
    </standOff>
</TEI>
